When I was a kid, my parents would tell me,
عندما كنت طفلا، كان والداي دائما ما يقولان لي،
"You can make a mess, but you have to clean up after yourself."
"يمكنك أن تصنع الفوضى ولكن عليك أن تُنظّف ذلك بنفسك."
So freedom came with responsibility.
إذن كانت الحرية ممزوجة بالمسؤولية.
But my imagination would take me to all these wonderful places,
ولكن مخيلتي تأخذني إلى كل تلك الأماكن الرائعة،
where everything was possible.
حيث كان كل شيء ممكنا.
So I grew up in a bubble of innocence --
لذلك ترعرعت في فقاعة من البراءة --
or a bubble of ignorance, I should say,
أو دعوني أقول فقاعة من الجهل،
because adults would lie to us to protect us from the ugly truth.
لأن الكبار دائما ما يكذبون علينا لحمايتنا من الحقيقة المرة.
And growing up, I found out that adults make a mess,
وعندما كبرت، اكتشفت أن البالغين يتسببون بالفوضى،
and they're not very good at cleaning up after themselves.
وليسوا جيدين في تنظيف أشيائهم.
Fast forward, I am an adult now,
ومع مرور الوقت، أنا بالغ الآن،
and I teach citizen science and invention at the Hong Kong Harbour School.
وأُدرّس علوم المواطن والاختراع بمدرسة هونغ كونغ هاربر.
And it doesn't take too long
ولم نستغرق وقتا طويلا
before my students walk on a beach and stumble upon piles of trash.
حتى بدأ تلامذتي بالتجول على الشاطئ والتعثر بأكوام من القمامة.
So as good citizens, we clean up the beaches --
و كمواطنين صالحين، قمنا بتنظيف الشواطئ --
and no, he is not drinking alcohol, and if he is, I did not give it to him.
وهنا هو لا يشرب الكحول، وإن كان كذلك، فأنا لم أعطه ذلك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And so it's sad to say,
ومن المحزن القول،
but today more than 80 percent of the oceans have plastic in them.
ولكن اليوم أكثر من 80% من المحيطات تحتوي على البلاستيك.
It's a horrifying fact.
هذه حقيقة مروعة.
And in past decades,
وخلال العقود الماضية،
we've been taking those big ships out and those big nets,
قمنا بتجميع تلك السفن والشبكات الكبيرة،
and we collect those plastic bits that we look at under a microscope,
وكنا نجمع قطع البلاستيك لفحصها تحت المجهر،
and we sort them,
وقمنا بفرزها،
and then we put this data onto a map.
ثم قمنا بوضع البيانات على الخريطة.
But that takes forever, it's very expensive,
ولكن ذلك سيستغرق وقتا طويلا، وسيكلف تكلفة باهضة،
and so it's quite risky to take those big boats out.
لذلك استخراج تلك القوارب من المحيط خطر جدا.
So with my students, ages six to 15,
لذلك برفقة تلامذتي الذين تتراوح أعمارهم بين 6 و 15 سنة،
we've been dreaming of inventing a better way.
كنا نحلم باختراع طريقة أفضل.
So we've transformed our tiny Hong Kong classroom into a workshop.
لذلك حولنا قسمنا الصغير إلى ورشة عمل.
And so we started building this small workbench,
وبدأنا بصنع طاولة العمل،
with different heights, so even really short kids can participate.
بارتفاعات مختلفة حتى يتمكن الأطفال قصيري القامة من المشاركة.
And let me tell you, kids with power tools are awesome and safe.
ودعوني أُخبركم بأن الأطفال الحاملين لأدوات القوة هم آمنون ورائعون.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Not really.
ليس حقا.
And so, back to plastic.
و عودةّ إلى البلاستيك.
We collect this plastic and we grind it to the size we find it in the ocean,
نحن نجمع البلاستيك ونطحنه بالحجم الذي نجده به في المحيط،
which is very small because it breaks down.
وهو حجم صغير جدا لأنه يتفتت.
And so this is how we work.
و هذه طريقة عملنا.
I let the imaginations of my students run wild.
أُطلق العنان لمخيلة تلامذتي.
And my job is to try to collect the best of each kid's idea
وتكمن مهمتي في تجميع أحسن الأفكار التي يأتي بها الأطفال
and try to combine it into something that hopefully would work.
ومحاولة دمجها للخروج بشيء يمكن أن ينجح.
And so we have agreed that instead of collecting plastic bits,
ولقد اتفقنا عوضا عن جمع قطع البلاستيك،
we are going to collect only the data.
أن نقوم بجمع المعلومات فقط.
So we're going to get an image of the plastic with a robot --
إذن سنحصل على صورة للبلاستيك بواسطة الروبوت --
so robots, kids get very excited.
نعم روبوت، الأطفال يتحمسون لذلك.
And the next thing we do -- we do what we call "rapid prototyping."
والشيء التالي الذي نقوم به -- ما يُسمّى "النماذج الأولية السريعة."
We are so rapid at prototyping
فنحن سريعون في صنع النماذج الأولية
that the lunch is still in the lunchbox when we're hacking it.
لدرجة أن الطعام ما يزال في صندوق الطعام حين نقوم بقص ذلك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And we hack table lamps and webcams, into plumbing fixtures
ونقوم باستعمال مصابيح الطاولة وكاميرات الواب كأجهزة سمكرة
and we assemble that into a floating robot that will be slowly moving through water
ونقوم بتجميع كل ذلك في روبوت عائم يتحرك ببطئ عبر الماء
and through the plastic that we have there --
والبلاستيك الموجود هناك --
and this is the image that we get in the robot.
وهذه الصورة التي نحصل عليها في الروبوت.
So we see the plastic pieces floating slowly through the sensor,
لذلك نرى القطع البلاستيكية تطفو ببطء من خلال أجهزة الاستشعار،
and the computer on board will process this image,
وسوف يقوم الكمبيوتر بمعالجة الصورة،
and measure the size of each particle,
وقياس حجم كل جسيم،
so we have a rough estimate of how much plastic there is in the water.
وبالتالي لدينا تقدير تقريبي لكمية البلاستيك الموجودة بالمياه.
So we documented this invention step by step
لذلك وثقنا هذا الاختراع خطوة بخطوة
on a website for inventors called Instructables,
على موقع للمخترعين يُدعى "انستراكتبل"،
in the hope that somebody would make it even better.
على أمل تحسينه من قبل أحدهم.
What was really cool about this project was that the students saw a local problem,
ما أعجبني حقا في هذا المشروع هو فطنة الأطفال لمشكلة محلية،
and boom -- they are trying to immediately address it.
ومحاولتهم معالجتها على الفور.
[I can investigate my local problem]
[بإمكاني أن أتحقق من مشكلتي المحلية]
But my students in Hong Kong are hyperconnected kids.
ولكن تلامذتي في هونغ كونغ دائما ما كانوا على علم بكل التحديثات.
And they watch the news, they watch the Internet,
ويشاهدون الأخبار والإنترنت،
and they came across this image.
وتوصلوا إلى هذه الصورة.
This was a child, probably under 10, cleaning up an oil spill bare-handed,
هذا طفل على الأرجح عمره أقل من 10 سنوات، يقوم بتنظيف تسرّب نفط و هوعاري اليدين،
in the Sundarbans, which is the world's largest mangrove forest in Bangladesh.
في سونداربانس، وهي أكبر غابة لشجر المنغروف في بنغلاديش.
So they were very shocked,
لذلك كانوا مصدومين،
because this is the water they drink, this is the water they bathe in,
لأنه كان ذلك الماء الذي يشربونه ويستحمون به،
this is the water they fish in -- this is the place where they live.
والماء الذي يصطادون منه -- هذا هو المكان الذين يعيشون فيه.
And also you can see the water is brown, the mud is brown and oil is brown,
كما يمكنك رؤية اللون البني لكل من الماء والطين والنفط،
so when everything is mixed up,
لذا عندما تمتزج معا،
it's really hard to see what's in the water.
يُصبح من الصعب رؤية ما يوجد بالماء.
But, there's a technology that's rather simple,
ولكن توجد تقنية بسيطة نوعا ما،
that's called spectrometry,
وتسمّى" قياس الطيف"،
that allows you see what's in the water.
تُمكّنك هذه من رؤية ما يوجد بالماء.
So we built a rough prototype of a spectrometer,
لذلك قمنا بصنع نموذج تقريبي لسبكترومتر،
and you can shine light through different substances
ويمكنك تسليط الضوء عبر عدة مواد
that produce different spectrums,
والذي سينتج عنه أطياف مختلفة،
so that can help you identify what's in the water.
وهو ما سيمكنك من تحديد ما يوجد في الماء.
So we packed this prototype of a sensor,
لذلك وضّبنا هذا النموذج من جهاز الاستشعار،
and we shipped it to Bangladesh.
وقمنا بإرساله إلى بنغلاديش.
So what was cool about this project
ما كان ممتعا بخصوص هذا المشروع
was that beyond addressing a local problem,
أنه لم يعالج مشكلة محلية،
or looking at a local problem,
أو ينظر في مشكلة محلية،
my students used their empathy and their sense of being creative
وإنما استخدم تلامذتي عاطفتهم وحس الابداع
to help, remotely, other kids.
لمساعدة الأطفال الآخرين عن بعد.
[I can investigate a remote problem]
[بإمكاني استكشاف مشكلة بعيدة]
So I was very compelled by doing the second experiments,
لذلك كنت مجبورا على القيام بتجارب أخرى،
and I wanted to take it even further --
وأردت الذهاب إلى أبعد من ذلك --
maybe addressing an even harder problem, and it's also closer to my heart.
ربما معالجة مشكلة أكبر وأصعب، وذلك أقرب إلى قلبي.
So I'm half Japanese and half French,
أنا نصف ياباني ونصف فرنسي،
and maybe you remember in 2011 there was a massive earthquake in Japan.
وربما تتذكرون الزلزال الهائل الذي حصل في اليابان في 2011.
It was so violent that it triggered several giant waves --
لقد كان عنيفا جدا لدرجة أنه أثار عدة موجات عملاقة --
they are called tsunami --
وسُمّي بتسونامي --
and those tsunami destroyed many cities on the eastern coast of Japan.
ولقد دمر تسونامي العديد من المدن على الساحل الشرقي لليابان.
More than 14,000 people died in an instant.
وفي لحظة تُوفّي أكثر من 14000 شخص.
Also, it damaged the nuclear power plant of Fukushima,
كما دمرت محطة توليد الطاقة النووية في فوكوشيما،
the nuclear power plant just by the water.
تم تدمير المحطة فقط بالماء.
And today, I read the reports
واليوم قرأت التقارير
and an average of 300 tons
حيث يتسرب قرابة 300 طن
are leaking from the nuclear power plant into the Pacific Ocean.
من محطة توليد الطاقة النووية في المحيط الهادي.
And today the whole Pacific Ocean has traces of contamination of cesium-137.
واليوم لا زالت آثارسيزيوم 137 بالمحيط الهادي بأكمله.
If you go outside on the West Coast, you can measure Fukushima everywhere.
إذا ذهبت خارج الساحل الغربي، بإمكانك قياس فوكوشيما في كل مكان.
But if you look at the map, it can look like most of the radioactivity
ولكن إذا نظرت إلى الخريطة، يبدو أن معظم النشاط الإشعاعي
has been washed away from the Japanese coast,
قد اضمحلّ من الساحل الياباني،
and most of it is now -- it looks like it's safe, it's blue.
ويبدو آمنا وأزرق اللون.
Well, reality is a bit more complicated than this.
في الواقع، الحقيقة معقدة أكثر مما تبدو عليه.
So I've been going to Fukushima every year since the accident,
لقد كنت أذهب إلى فكوشيما كل عام منذ الحادث،
and I measure independently and with other scientists,
وأقوم بالقياس لوحدي وبصحبة علماء آخرين،
on land, in the river --
على الأرض وفي النهر --
and this time we wanted to take the kids.
وهذه المرة أردت إحضار الأطفال معي.
So of course we didn't take the kids, the parents wouldn't allow that to happen.
ولكن بالطبع لم نصطحبهم لأن أهلهم لن يوافقوا على ذلك بالطبع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But every night we would report to "Mission Control" --
ولكن كل ليلة نقوم بتقرير إلى "وحدة مراقبة المهمة" --
different masks they're wearing.
مختلف الأقنعة التي يرتدونها.
It could look like they didn't take the work seriously, but they really did
يبدو أنهم لم يأخذوا العمل على محمل الجد ولكنهم بالفعل قاموا بذلك
because they're going to have to live with radioactivity their whole life.
لأنه سيتوجب عليهم العيش مع النشاط الإشعاعي طوال حياتهم.
And so what we did with them
وما الذي قمنا به معهم
is that we'd discuss the data we collected that day,
هو مناقشة البيانات التي قمنا بتجميعها في ذلك اليوم،
and talk about where we should be going next --
ومناقشة الخطوة التالية --
strategy, itinerary, etc...
الاستراتيجية والمخطط، ...الخ
And to do this, we built a very rough topographical map
وللقيام بذلك، قمنا ببناء خريطة طبوغرافية
of the region around the nuclear power plant.
للمنطقة حول محطة توليد الطاقة النووية.
And so we built the elevation map,
وبالتالي قمنا ببناء خريطة الارتفاع،
we sprinkled pigments to represent real-time data for radioactivity,
ولقد قمنا بوضع الطلاء لتمثيل بيانات النشاط الإشعاعي،
and we sprayed water to simulate the rainfall.
وقمنا برش الماء لتمثيل هطول الأمطار.
And with this we could see that the radioactive dust
وبهذا يُمكن أن نرى بأن الغبار المُشع
was washing from the top of the mountain into the river system,
بدأ ينحدر من قمة الجبل وصولا إلى نظام النهر،
and leaking into the ocean.
ثم يتسرب إلى المحيط.
So it was a rough estimate.
كان ذلك تقديرا تقريبيا.
But with this in mind, we organized this expedition,
ولكن مع أخذ هذا في الاعتبار، نظمنا هذه الحملة،
which was the closest civilians have been to the nuclear power plant.
حيث كان المواطنون قريبين جدا من محطة توليد الطاقة النووية.
We are sailing 1.5 kilometers away from the nuclear power plant,
لقد كنا نُبحر على بعد 1.5 كم من محطة توليد الطاقة النووية،
and with the help of the local fisherman,
وبمساعدة الصيادين المحليين،
we are collecting sediment from the seabed
قمنا بجمع الرواسب من قاع البحر
with a custom sediment sampler we've invented and built.
وفقا لمواصفات عينات من الرواسب قمنا باختراعها وصنعها.
We pack the sediment into small bags,
جمعنا الرواسب في أكياس صغيرة،
we then dispatch them to hundreds of small bags
ثم قسّمناهم على مئات الأكياس الصغيرة
that we send to different universities,
التي قمنا بإرسالها إلى مختلف الجامعات،
and we produce the map of the seabed radioactivity,
وقمنا بصنع خريطة للنشاط الإشعاعي لقاع البحر،
especially in estuaries where the fish will reproduce,
خصوصا في مصبات الأنهار حيث تتكاثر الأسماك،
and I will hope that we will have improved
ونأمل بأننا قد قمنا بتحسين
the safety of the local fishermen and of your favorite sushi.
سلامة الصيادين المحليين والسوشي المفضل لديكم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You can see a progression here --
بإمكانكم رؤية تطور هنا --
we've gone from a local problem to a remote problem to a global problem.
انطلقنا من مشكلة محلية إلى مشكلة بعيدة إلى مشكلة عالمية.
And it's been super exciting to work at these different scales,
ولقد كان من الممتع العمل على مختلف المستويات،
with also very simple, open-source technologies.
باستعمال تقنيات بسيطة.
But at the same time, it's been increasingly frustrating
ولكن في نفس الوقت، كان ذلك محبطا على نحو متزايد
because we have only started to measure the damage that we have done.
لأننا قمنا بقياس الضرر الذي تسببنا به.
We haven't even started to try to solve the problems.
لم نبدأ حتى في إيجاد حل لهذه المشاكل.
And so I wonder if we should just take a leap
وأتساءل ما إذا ينبغي القيام بقفزة
and try to invent better ways to do all these things.
وتجربة اختراع طرق أفضل للقيام بكل هذه الأشياء.
And so the classroom started to feel a little bit small,
لذلك بدأنا نشعر بصغر حجم القسم،
so we found an industrial site in Hong Kong,
حيث وجدنا موقعا صناعيا في هونغ كونغ،
and we turned it into the largest mega-space
وحولناه إلى مساحة كبيرة تهتم
focused on social and environmental impact.
بالأثر الاجتماعي والبيئي.
It's in central Hong Kong,
حيث يقع بوسط هونغ كونغ،
and it's a place we can work with wood, metal, chemistry,
وهو مكان نستطيع أن نعمل فيه بالخشب والمعدن والكيمياء،
a bit of biology, a bit of optics,
قليلا من البيولوجيا وعلم البصريات،
basically you can build pretty much everything there.
يمكنك أن تبني كل شيء هناك.
And its a place where adults and kids can play together.
وهو مكان حيث يمكن لكل البالغين والأطفال اللعب معا.
It's a place where kids' dreams can come true,
هو مكان حيث يمكن لأحلام الأطفال أن تتحقق،
with the help of adults,
بمساعدة من البالغين،
and where adults can be kids again.
و يمكن للبالغين أن يعودوا أطفالا .
Student: Acceleration! Acceleration!
التلامذة: أسرع ! أسرع !
Cesar Harada: We're asking questions such as,
سيزار هارادا: نسأل أسئلة مثل،
can we invent the future of mobility with renewable energy?
هل يمكننا اختراع مستقبل "التنقل" باستعمال الطاقة المتجددة؟
For example.
على سبيل المثال.
Or, can we help the mobility of the aging population
أو، هل يمكننا المساعدة في تنقل الفئة المسنة
by transforming very standard wheelchairs into cool, electric vehicles?
بتحويل الكراسي المتحركة العادية إلى سيارات كهربائية ممتعة؟
So plastic, oil and radioactivity are horrible, horrible legacies,
إذن يُمثّل كلّ من البلاستيك والنفط والنشاط الإشعاعي إرثا مُروّعا،
but the very worst legacy that we can leave our children is lies.
ولكن أفظع إرث يُمكن أن نتركه لأطفالنا هو الأكاذيب.
We can no longer afford to shield the kids from the ugly truth
لا يمكننا توفير الحماية لأطفالنا من الحقيقة المرة
because we need their imagination to invent the solutions.
لأننا في حاجة إلى مخيلتهم لابتكار الحلول.
So citizen scientists, makers, dreamers --
سواء كنا علماء وصنّاع وحالمين -- اقتباس"الخيال أهم من المعرفة" آينشتاين
we must prepare the next generation
يجب علينا إعداد الجيل القادم
that cares about the environment and people,
الذي يهتم بالناس والبيئة،
and that can actually do something about it.
ويمكننا بالفعل القيام بشيء حيال ذلك.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)